Planned Parenthood League of Massachusetts, 1859-2002 (bulk 1916-1960)
Sophia Smith Collection
- SERIES III. CENTRAL ADMINISTRATIVE FILES 1916-2002, 13 linear ft.
  In 1928 the Emergency Defense Committee was renamed the Birth Control League of Massachusetts (BCLM). The second subseries, Birth Control League of Massachusetts contains information from its annual meetings and dinners including minutes (1930-39) and annual reports (1930-39), along with records of eleven of the BCLM's committees including the Executive Committee. The section on the Mother's Health Committee, created in 1932 to be responsible for the Mother's Health Office, consists of correspondence, meeting agendas and minutes, form letters, and publicity material concerning BCLM sponsored clinics and the 1942 referendum. Financial records of the League include information on financial campaigns, budgets and expenses, finances for the Defense Fund, treasurer's reports, and finance committee material. The Mother's Health Office (also called the Mother's Health Committee Office) was organized in 1931 to oversee the clinics. Of particular interest are materials related to administrative policy and planning; accounts and finances; annual, semiannual and monthly clinic reports; minutes of committee meetings; management policies; patient instructions and referrals; publicity releases; and speeches. There is also information related to the police raids that closed these clinics in 1937, the arrest of the staff, and the legal battle that followed. There is additional information on the clinic closings in SERIES XI. LEGISLATIVE FILES, SERIES VIII. CLIPPINGS AND ARTICLES, and SERIES X. MICROFILM. The personnel section contains reports of Mary White, education director (1930-41), and field director Doris Rutledge (1937-38). The plans and policy section contains information on the BCLM name change. In the publicity section there is information on the advertising dispute in 1935 between Blanche Ames Ames and Cornelia James Cannon (there is additional material about this in SERIES VIII. MICROFILM), financial issues, form letters, newspapers, press releases, printed material, and radio campaigns of the League. League research material on contraceptives is also included in this series.
  The BCLM was renamed the Massachusetts Mothers' Health Council in 1939. The third subseries, Massachusetts Mothers' Health Council (MMHC), consists of annual meeting reports; minutes of committee and staff meetings; administrative records; reports of executive, field, and program directors; and publicity materials. Reports, brochures, press releases, and a copy of Margaret Sanger's speech in support of the Initiative Petition campaign document her 1940 tour of Massachusetts and the efforts to prevent her speaking. There are also files of mailings, reports, and copies of speeches about the referendum campaign; and a collection of printed materials and articles on birth control subjects.
  The next three subseries contain the records of committees established to support MMHC and PPLM activities. The Clergymen's Advisory Committee subseries consists of documents relating to the referendum campaigns, correspondence and statements on birth control arranged by denomination, copies of sermons on birth control, newsletters, pamphlets, publicity materials, and reports of meetings with the PPLM Executive Committee. The Men's Committee for Medical Rights subseries contains correspondence, memoranda, and other papers relating mainly to its fundraising activities. The Physicians Committee for the Defense of Medical Rights subseries consists of correspondence, Executive Committee minutes and lists of members, lists of physicians, form letters, a questionnaire, press releases, and publications of the Committee.
  The MMHC was renamed the Planned Parenthood League of Massachusetts in 1945. The seventh subseries, Planned Parenthood League of Massachusetts (PPLM), consists of correspondence, minutes of annual meetings and Board of Directors' meetings, papers from other committees, programs, reports of the executive and state directors and the field representative, papers from the Speakers' Bureau, and copies of speeches. There are reports of the Benson and Benson Survey of 1940 and other public opinion polls and a questionnaire about a possible referendum in 1954. The few photographs of PPLM workers are included in this subseries in the publicity section.
- SERIES IV. RELATED ORGANIZATIONS 1918-68, 6.25 linear ft
  This series consist two subseries: Affiliated organizations and Miscellaneous organizations. The first contains material on four organizations with which the PPLM was affiliated beginning in 1928. There are four sections: American Birth Control League (ABCL), Birth Control League of America (later the Planned Parenthood Federation of America (BCFA/PPFA)), Planned Parenthood League of Connecticut, Planned Parenthood of Western Massachusetts, and Planned Parenthood - World Population (a merger in 1960 between PPFA and World Population Emergency Campaign). The ABCL section contains annual and Board of Directors meetings and minutes, by-laws, clinic standards, reports, printed material, conferences, and publicity. The largest section, BCFA/PPFA, consists of 5.5 linear ft. of records. There is a complete set of minutes of Board of Directors meetings as well as memoranda, reports, correspondence, and other materials about PPFA activities. Also of interest are exchanges of correspondence and information on working with African-Americans, financial procedures, and other organizational matters. Planned Parenthood of Connecticut contains correspondence with PPLM, meeting minutes and reports, and publicity and publications. Planned Parenthood of Western Massachusetts contains a small amount of miscellaneous material from the late 1960s. In 1961 the population crisis debate, along with funding shortages, convinced PPFA to merge with the World Population Emergency Campaign, a citizens' fund-raising organization, to become PPFA-World Population. This section contains information on family planning legislation, a National Conference on Family Planning (1966), and a regional workshop.
  The second subseries, Miscellaneous organizations, contains small amounts of materials related to nine additional birth control organizations: Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau, Citizens Committee for Planned Parenthood, Human Betterment Association, International Planned Parenthood Federation, Margaret Sanger Research Bureau, Massachusetts Central Health Council, National Committee for Planned Parenthood, National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control, and Voluntary Parenthood League. The Margaret Sanger Research Bureau material includes correspondence and notes of PPLM president Lorraine Campbell.
- SERIES V. CONFERENCE FILES 1934-67, 3 linear ft.
  This series is divided into two subseries: Planned Parenthood League of Massachusetts and Miscellaneous. The first subseries consists of material related to five conferences sponsored by BLM, MMHC, and PPLM. They are organized alphabetically by title. The bulk of this subseries is composed of the New England Conference on Tomorrow's Children which the PPLM sponsored for three subsequent summers between 1940 and 1942. These records include correspondence, conference papers, planning and arrangement materials, proceedings, programs, publicity, and documents related to speakers. In addition there is material on PPLM's Population Problems in a Free World (1946); two conferences sponsored by BCLM (Community Leaders Conference on Birth Control (1938) and New England Conference on Birth Control and the Community (1936)), and Two State Legislative Conference sponsored by MMHC. In the Miscellaneous subseries there is material on twelve additional birth control and population related conferences sponsored by various organizations including the Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau, U.S. government agencies, and the White House.
- SERIES VI. LEGISLATIVE FILES 1917-70, 7 linear ft.
  This series contains legal documents and other papers documenting PPLM'S (and its predecessor organizations) efforts to change the state laws on birth control. It is divided into five subseries: History and background materials, Initiative and Referendum Campaign, House and Senate Bills, Miscellaneous legislative efforts, and Connecticut legislative files.
  The History and background material subseries contains material related to the history of birth control legislation in Massachusetts as well as background material related to the legislative efforts of the 1940s. It includes correspondence related to and drafts and final versions of "Birth Control and the Massachusetts Law" produced by PPLM in 1941 and revised in 1950. There is also as well as a history of attempts to change the Massachusetts law (1959); and articles, notes, and correspondence related to test case research. Of particular interest is case material related to the trials that resulted from the raids on the Brookline and Salem clinics, Lewis Corbett (a pharmacist arrested for selling birth control devices), Caroline Gardner vs. the Commonwealth of Massachusetts (the raid on the North Shore Mother's Health Office), Antoinette Konikow (1928), as well as miscellaneous legal opinions. In addition there is information on the dismissal of doctors from hospitals in Massachusetts and Connecticut and New York for espousing birth control. Of particular interest is a section on Legislation which includes Hearings on the Committee on Public Health and the Doctor's Bill; hearings statements and miscellaneous material on House Bill 2035 (Initiative Petition to allow physicians to provide medical contraceptive care to married persons for the protections of life or health); Cummins Vail Bill (the first legislative attempt to change the birth control laws), 1924; and the Sheppard Towner Act (The Promotion of the welfare and hygiene of maternity and infancy), 1928. There is also documentation of information on cases pertaining to birth control in other states and foreign countries including U.S. vs. One Package (importation of condoms), 1936.
  The Initiative and referendum campaign subseries contains three sections: Field files; Initiative and Referendum Campaign, 1940-41; and Initiative and Referendum Campaign, 1947-48. The Field files consist of correspondence, notes, and data collected for the two Initiative and Referendum campaigns. It is arranged alphabetically by county. The two Initiative and Referendum Campaign sections contain program and policy reports, field reports, lists of workers and contributors, and contacts for the 1942 and 1948 campaigns. Also included are briefs, copies of cases and bills, and resource information and voting records by county for the 1947-48 campaign. Printed materials include form letters, press releases, copies of house bills, and publicity materials. The latter includes publicity materials of the opposition. There are also copies of the original signatures on the petitions used in these campaigns. There is more complete documentation of the Initiative and Referendum campaign in 1948 than for the earlier one.
  The House and Senate Bills subseries contains memoranda, notes, statements, correspondence, financial records, bulletins and newsletters. It also includes drafts related to the Committee to Support House Bill #1401 (an act allowing the dissemination of birth control information by registered physicians and pharmacists), House Bills #418 (a bill to remove the word "married" from the birth control law), and House Bill #2965 (provides that only physicians can administer or prescribe contraception). Also included is material on the House Special Study Commission Report (1965), miscellaneous legal documents, lists and statements, and related notes by Loraine Leeson Campbell (1965-69).
  The Miscellaneous legislative efforts subseries contains information on efforts following the Initiative and Referendum Campaigns of the 1940s. There are statements by religious leaders and physicians about birth control, hearings, reports, and correspondence about legislation with state senators. Research materials and correspondence relating to the consideration of whether to undertake a third initiative and petition campaign round out this subseries.
  The Connecticut legislative files subseries contains information related to attempts to legalize birth control in Connecticut. It includes printed material, general statutes, histories, house bills, and hearings. Of particular interest are correspondence; briefs, motions and appeals related to specific cases, particularly Connecticut vs. Certain Contraceptive Materials (1940); Griswold, Buxton vs. Connecticut (1959-64); Nelson, Goodrich, McTernan vs. Connecticut (1940); and Tileston vs. Ullman (1942-43). A collaborative effort on possible test cases with Massachusetts is documented by correspondence, memoranda, and reports. Additional material can be found in SERIES IV. RELATED ORGANIZATIONS, SERIES VII. RESOURCE FILES, and SERIES VIII. CLIPPINGS AND ARTICLES.
- SERIES VII. RESOURCE FILES 1859-1971, 6.75 linear ft.
  This series is a subject file arranged alphabetically that includes journal articles, pamphlets, statements, newsletters, clippings, and some correspondence. It is the result of the BCLM's practice of collecting pertinent articles for research purposes and as a resource for their efforts to change Massachusetts legislation. It was further developed by staff members as PPLM extended its interest and outreach. The file provided material to distribute among staff members for elucidation of issues, for ideas for speeches, and to provide background material for publicity. Articles and pamphlets that could easily be found in the holdings of the Smith College Libraries or other local collections have been de-accessioned. The subjects are wide-ranging and include those related to housing, employment, public health, marriage, population issues, family planning, and religion (especially birth control and the Catholic Church). There is also a large file of material on organizations, countries, and states. A section on individuals, including Robert Latou Dickinson, John F. Kennedy, Gregory Pincus, John Rock, and Margaret Sanger, is also of interest
- SERIES VIII. CLIPPINGS AND ARTICLES 1916-70, 3.25 linear ft.
  This series consists of three subseries: Notebook of article digests, Subject files and Chronological files.
  The first subseries consists of a notebook of digests of articles about birth control (1916-38) probably compiled by PPLM staff. The second consists of clippings arranged alphabetically by subject. Of particular interest are the files on abortion, Blacks and birth control, Catholic Church, clinic raids, Connecticut, contraception, population, and Margaret Sanger. Many of these subjects are related to each other and are also found elsewhere in the records and in the chronological files in the next subseries. The third subseries consist of a group of clippings arranged chronologically (1934-69).
- SERIES IX. OVERSIZE MATERIALS 1859-1966, .75 linear ft.
  This series consists of two subseries: Sound recordings and Miscellaneous oversize materials.
  Sound recordings contains forty-two sound recordings (thirty-three 16" records and nine 12" records) of broadcasts aired by the Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau and the PPLM between 1938 and 1951. The PPLM broadcasts primarily relate to the referendum campaign. Because these recordings cannot be transferred to a usable format at this time, they are closed to research.
  The second subseries, Miscellaneous oversize materials consists of one box of items removed from the main body of the records and several items located in the flat files. Of particular interest in Box 22 is an 1859 issue of the newspaper The Clipper that includes advertisements for condoms. Separation sheets show the original locations of these oversize items.
- SERIES X. MICROFILM 1931-61, 7 reels .5 linear ft.
  This series consists of forty-five scrapbooks that were microfilmed for preservation purposes. Lorraine Leeson Campbell donated scrapbooks number 1-29 and 31-39, and numbers 30, 40-45 were donated to PPLM by Margaret Sanger. Topics of interest in these scrapbooks include the Doctor's Bill; the Blanche Ames Ames/Cornelia James Cannon controversy; Blanche Ames Ames and the Roman Catholic Church; Margaret Sanger's speeches (including the Holyoke Affair), trips abroad, arrest and trials; the MMHC, ABCL, BCCRB, BCFA, and PPFA.
- SERIES I. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Staff
    - Ames, Blanche Ames 1918-58, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - Anderson, Reginald 1947-48 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Auchincloss, Samuel 1961-65, undated, [See also Sagoff, Hazel] (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Baker, Ruth C. 1932-40 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Banay, Isabel 1955-56 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Benson, Marguerite 1934-38 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Belisle, Eugene
      - 1939-40 (Box 2, Folder 1-13)
      - 1941-43, undated (Box 3, Folder 1-14)
    - Borden, Elizabeth B. 1940-45, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Bradford, Dorothy W. 1936-42, undated (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
    - Bradford, Robert 1934-65, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Campbell, Lorraine Leeson
      - By date
        - 1934-52 (Box 4, Folder 5-16)
        - 1953-76, undated (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
      - By subject
        - Diaphragms 1954 (Box 5, Folder 5)
        - Population 1946-60, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Cannon, Cornelia James 1934-42, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Clothier, Florence, M.D. 1940-61, undated (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
    - Daniel, Thelma1964-65 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Davis, Caroline L. Carter (Box 6, Folder 2-12)
      - 1931-37 (Box 6, Folder 2-12)
      - 1938-40, undated (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
    - Des Granges, Mrs. Donald 1956-60 (Box 7, Folder 4-6)
    - East, Mary L. 1928-32 (Box 7, Folder 7-10)
    - Everts, William P. 1932-40 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Faulkner, Mary duPont 1933-61, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Fisk, Amelia 1944-48 (Box 7, Folder 13-14)
    - Goodwin, Mary B.1932-34 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Hartl, Elizabeth 1953 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Howland, Alice F. 1933-60 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Hawkridge, Linda M.
      - 1932-37 (Box 8, Folder 4-14)
      - 1938-42, undated (Box 9, Folder 1-4)
    - Jack, Cerise Carmen 1918?, 1928 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - McGann, Marion D. 1932-39, undated (Box 9, Folder 6-8)
    - Plank, Stephen 1966-68 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Rutledge, Doris L. 1936-43, undated (Box 9, Folder 10-13)
    - Sagoff, Hazel
      - Auchinchloss, Samuel 1962-65, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Bradford, Robert 1962-65 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Guttmacher, Alan F. 1962-69 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Human Betterment Association 1961-67, [see also SERIES VII. RESOURCE FILE - Organizations] (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - Plank, Stephen 1962-68 (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - Planned Parenthood-World Population 1967-68 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - Sturgis, Somers, M.D 1960-68 (Box 10, Folder 7)
      - Miscellaneous 1942-69, undated (Box 10, Folder 8-9)
    - Sax, Karl, M.D 1944-64 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Seabury, Frida 1935-42, undated (Box 10, Folder 11-12)
    - Smith, Ruth P.1948-55 (Box 10, Folder 13-14)
    - Snedeker, Lendon, M.D. 1955-57 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Tauber, Esther 1948-56, 1964 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Taylor, Margaret C. 1934-48, undated (Box 11, Folder 1-7)
    - Trent, Kathryn1944 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Vaughan, Virginia 1941-42, undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - White, Mary M.
      - 1934-37 (Box 11, Folder 10-14)
      - 1938-42, undated (Box 12, Folder 1-5)
  - Miscellaneous individuals
    - A 1929-46 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Aaron, Janet 1948, 1965, undated (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Adams, Letitia D., M.D. 1934-37 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - B 1933-38, undated (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Bailey, Helen D. 1935, 1942, 1951, undated (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Baker, Charlotte S. 1932-35, undated (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Banay, Isabel 1955-58 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Bangs, Catherine C. 1934-35 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Barney, J. Dellinger 1935-38, 1946-50 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Barrows, Walter A. 1937-47 (Box 12, Folder 15-16)
    - Bassett, Edward D. 1935 (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Bertheau, Rudolph 1939, 1941 (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Blanchard, Arthur F. 1941 (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Blanchard, Paul 1951, [see also SERIES III. CENTRAL ADMINSTRATIVE FILES - PPLM - Annual Meetings, 1951] (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Boughton, Alice C. 1931-32 (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - Bowditch, Mabel 1935, 1937, undated (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - Boynton, Gordon 1948-50, undated (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - Bradford, Standish 1939 (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - Bradley, Mabel W. 1936-41, undated (Box 12, Folder 25)
    - Brittain, Vera 1934 (Box 12, Folder 26)
    - Brownell, Constance 1936-37 (Box 12, Folder 27)
    - Buck, Pearl S. 1942 (Box 12, Folder 28)
    - Burch, Guy Irving1940-41 (Box 12, Folder 29)
    - Butler, Jessie Haver 1934 (Box 12, Folder 30)
    - C 1921-60, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Calderone, Mary Steichen, M.D.1958-60 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Cannon, Ida M. 1939-41 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Cannon, Walter M. 1942-43, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Carmichael, Leonard, M.D. 1939 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Coolidge, Alison 1941-42, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Cowan, Fairman C. 1947-56 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Craig, Margaret C. 1935-39, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Crocker, N.S. 1936-40, undated (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Cutler, Leslie B. 1939-48 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - D 1928-56 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Damon, Cecil 1937-41 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - De Normandie, Robert Latou., M.D. 1935-49 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - DeVilbiss, Lydia Allen, M.D. 1933-48 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Dickinson, Robert L., M.D. 1929-40 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Dodge, Robert G. 1937-41 (Box 13, Folder 16-18)
    - duPont, Pierre S. 1947 (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - Durant, Will 1939 (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - E 1930-60, undated (Box 13, Folder 21)
    - Elder, Samuel J. 1917 (Box 13, Folder 22)
    - Eliot, Frederick May, 1937-40 (Box 13, Folder 23)
    - Ernst, Morris 1938-58 (Box 13, Folder 24)
    - F 1932-51 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Farnsworth, R. H. 1941-42, undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Faulkner, James M., M.D. 1942-50, 1965 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Faxon, Nathaniel W., M.D. 1935-52 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Feld, Eliza McCormick 1949-51 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Field, Richard H. 1939-42, 1960 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Forbes, A. W. 1940-42 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Frothingham, Channing 1938, 1943-53 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - G 1932-58 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Galleani, Ilia, M.D. 1935-37 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Gamble, Clarence, M.D. 1934-48, undated (Box 14, Folder 11-12)
    - Gerould, Virginia Vaughn 1939-42 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Gilman, Bradley B. 1939-42 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Guttmacher, Alan F., M.D. 1942, 1956-58, [see also: Staff-Hazel Sagoff] (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - H 1930-54 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Hall, Murray F. 1932-35 (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Hanau, Stella 1932-37 (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Hepburn, Katherine Houghton 1936-38 (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Herter, Christian A. 1939, 1941 (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Hill, Dorothy P. 1935-38 (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - Hilliard, Curtis M. 1940-47 (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Himes, Norman E. 1931-41 (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - Hoar, Samuel 1935-41 (Box 14, Folder 24)
    - Hodson, Cora B. 1932 (Box 14, Folder 25)
    - Hopkins, M. S. 1935-37 (Box 14, Folder 26)
    - Humphrey, Hubert H. 1959 (Box 14, Folder 27)
    - Huntington, Ellsworth 1934-36 (Box 14, Folder 28)
    - Huse, P. B. P. 1932, 1938-41 (Box 14, Folder 29)
    - I-J 1933-55, undated (Box 14, Folder 30)
    - Jaffe, Frederick 1959-61 (Box 14, Folder 31)
    - Jenkins, Eleanor C. 1945-46 (Box 14, Folder 32)